A Finding Aid to the Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne Papers, 1910s-1980, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne papers
1910s-1980
Archives of American Art
Bengelsdorf, Rosalind, 1916-1979
AAA.bengrosa
Archival Resource Key
3.2 Linear feet
The papers of painter and critic Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne measure 3.2 linear feet and date from the 1910s to 1980. The papers document Browne's career through biographical materials including sketches and photographs, correspondence with friends, artists, and institutions, writings, professional files, and printed material.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter and critic Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne measure 3.2 linear feet and date from the 1910s to 1980. The papers document Browne's career through biographical materials including sketches and photographs, correspondence with friends, artists, and institutions, writings, professional files, and printed material.
Biographical material includes a transcript of an interview with Susan C. Larsen. Correspondence includes letters from Ethel Baziotes, Romare Bearden, Sid Gotcliffe, and Philip Evergood. Writings include sound recordings of a monologue by Browne concerning her husband Byron Browne and Sam Kootz. Professional files may include correspondence, printed material, writings, and agreements relating to Browne's various roles as a critic, an artist, and an educator. Of note are files on the American Abstract Artists organization and the WPA Federal Art Project.
Existence and Location of Copies
Material microfilmed on 35mm microfilm reels 2013-2016 is available for use at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Biographical / Historical
Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne (1916-1979) was an abstract painter, critic, educator, and writer active in New York City, New York.
Born in New York City in 1916, Rosalind Bengelsdorf studied at the Art Students' League as a teenager. She continued her study of art under her mentor Hans Hofmann, developing her artistic beliefs and style of abstract painting. In 1936, she became a founding member of the American Abstract Artists of New York City. That same year, she joined the Works Progress Administration (WPA) Federal Arts Project and completed murals at the Central Nurses Home on Welfare Island under Burgoyne Diller.
In 1940, Bengelsdorf married fellow artist Byron Browne, and the couple decided that she would end her art career to focus on teaching and writing. Browne subsequently worked as an art critic for Pictures on Exhibit, The New York Star, and Woman's Day and taught at the New School for Social Research until the late-1970s. After her husband's death in 1961, she returned to painting.
Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne died in Manhattan in 1979.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 1978 and 1979 by Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne and her son, Stephen B. Browne.
Related Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds an interview of Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne conducted 1968 January 29, by Irving Sandler. Also found are the papers of Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne's husband: the Byron Browne papers, 1930-1963.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1910s-1980 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1929-1979 (Box 1, 0.6 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1934-1978 (Box 2; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Professional Files, 1930-1978 (Boxes 2-3; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1930-1979 (Box 4; 0.2 linear feet)
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Art critics -- New York (State) -- New York; Educators -- New York (State) -- New York; Women artists; Women painters; Women art critics; Women educators; Sound recordings; Interviews; Browne, Byron, 1907-1961; O'Connor, Francis V.; American Abstract Artists
- Biographical Material, 1910s-1980; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Found are biographical materials as well as scattered artworks, an interview, personal business records, and photographs. Artworks consist of unsigned pencil and pastel sketches and sketchbooks. Biographical materials include address books, resumes, passports, ID and membership cards to various New York City institutions, report cards and school projects, and a wallet containing Mexican coins, circa 1910. Personal business records consist of rental agreements, tenant organization material, vehicle records, and receipts.
  - Address Books, 1930-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Artwork, Collage, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Artwork, Sketchbook, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Artwork, Sketches, circa 1930-circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Sketches and Resumes, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Health Records, 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Identification Cards and Passports, circa 1916-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interview Transcript, with Susan Carol Larsen, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Membership Cards, 1934-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal Business Records, 1931-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Photographs, of Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne, circa 1936-circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, of Exhibition, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, of Works of Art, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - School Records, 1924-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-19)
  - Wallet, 1910s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1929-1979; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1
  Browne's correspondence is with family, friends, institutions, and artists. Found are letters from Ethel Baziotes, Romare Bearden, Philip Evergood, Nancy Galantiere, Sid Gotcliffe, Lee Hall, Jacob Kainen, Lucien Lareau, and Aline Saarinen. Also found are letters from graduate students taught by Browne in the 1970s. Some greeting and holiday cards contain original artworks by friends.
  - General, circa 1940-circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - General, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General, 1930-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - General, 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - General, 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - General, 1960-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - General, 1970-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - Graduate Students and Researchers, 1972-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Greeting and Holiday Cards, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Writings and Notes, 1934-1978; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2
  Series contains writings by Browne including typed drafts of works, some with annotations, and an illustrated mockup for an unpublished work entitled Is Santa Claus Real?. Sound recordings are of a monologue by Browne about her husband Byron Browne and artist Sam Kootz, dating from 1971.
  - "Abstract Art and the WPA in New York," by Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "American Abstract Artists," by Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne, Annotated, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Autobiography, Incomplete, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Is Santa Claus Real?, by Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Lecture, for Artists Union, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Monologue, by Rosalind Bengelsdorf Browne and Byron Browne, 1971-1977; Archival Resource Key; 4 Cassettes Two cassettes are duplicate copies of the monologue recording. (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Notebook and Notes, 1934-circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Professional Files, 1930-1978; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Professional files form the bulk of the collection and encompass Browne's career as a painter, educator, critic and writer.
  A file for American Abstract Artists comments on Browne's affiliation as a founding member of the organization and includes correspondence, printed material, and drafts of questionnaires, some of which are photocopies. Works Progress Administration material contains scattered information on Browne's work on murals at the Central Nurses Home.
  Also found are files for schools at which Browne taught, most notably for the New School for Social Research; exhibition files; and files for publications such as the Encyclopedia Judaica, The New York Star, and Pictures on Exhibit. Of note is a file for Francis V. O'Connor's compiled work on the New Deal Art Projects in which Browne is included.
  - Advertising Copy, 1939-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Abstract Artists, 1936-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Annot Art School, 1934-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Archives of American Art, 1965-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Art News, 1950-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Art Students' League, 1930-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Encyclopedia Judaica, 1944-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Exhibition, "7 American Women: The Depression Decade," Vassar College Art Gallery, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition, "Geometric Abstraction of the 1930s," Zabriskie Gallery, 1972-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition, "The Survivors: Federal Arts Projects of the 1930s in New York State," Gallery Association of New York State Inc., 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition, University of New Mexico, 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ford Foundation, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Fourth Dimension Holiday, Inc., 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Job Applications, 1948-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The New Deal Art Projects: an Anthology of Memoirs, by Francis V. O'Connor, 1964-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - The New School for Social Research, 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-10)
  - The New York Star, 1948-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - New York University, 1952-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
  - Provincetown Advocate, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Pictures on Exhibit, "Gallery Previews in New York", 1946-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Teaching Concepts and Methods, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1977-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Woman's Day, 1965-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Works Progress Administration, 1937-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Printed Material, 1930-1979; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 4
  Printed materials include clippings and exhibition materials concerning Browne's career as an artist, critic, and writer. Also found is scattered exhibition material on her husband, Byron Browne. Travel souvenirs include maps and brochures.
  Arrangement
  Formerly, clippings were arranged in the form of a scrapbook which was dismantled before microfilming.
  - Clippings, 1930-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1932-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Travel Souvenirs, circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)